Fine Arts collection, Inclusive: 1903,1936,1937, 1975, 1982, undated, Bulk: undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
- Texas, 2
  - Places, 9
    - Comanche Nation, 12; Unknown, Artist
      Picture of a Letter; framed 17.25 X 21 in.; unframed 15.25 X 19 in.
    - Courthouse Building, 13; Campbell, Janet
      Watercolor; framed 16.5 X 10 in.; unframed 21 X 14.5 in.
    - Painting of a House, 14; Campbell, Janet
    - The Madison Cooper House, 18th and Austin, Waco, Texas, 15; Jeffrey, Jaclyn
      Watercolor; framed 20.5 X 16 in.; unframed 13.5 X 10.5 in.
    - The First Surgical Operation in North America: Cabeza de Vaca-- Taking the arrowhead from the Indian's chest, in West Texas in the year 1535, 16; Lea, Tom
      Alvar Núñez Cabeza de Vaca, an early Spanish explorer in the Southern United States, was part of a group sent to establish a Spanish colony between Florida and Mexico in 1527. Through an error, a group of these explorers who had landed in Florida were abandoned by their ships. This group of 250-300 men then spent the next nine years traveling over 2,400 miles to Mexico City. They had many adventures with American Indians along the way. One group of Indians they encountered believed Cabeza de Vaca was a healer, and compelled him to treat their sick. This painting shows Cabeza de Vaca performing the first surgical operation ever performed by a white man on the North American continent in 1535.
      Related Resources
      Related references
      Chipman, Donald E. "Cabeza de Vaca, Alvar Nunez." Handbook of Texas Online http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/fca06. Accessed March 14, 2013.
      Indians, Treatment of -- America -- History.; Núñez Cabeza de Vaca, Alvar, 16th cent.
      ?; framed 21 X 17 in.; unframed 8.5 X 11 in.
    - Texas Live Oaks with Bluebonnets, 17; Cuprien, F.W.
      Painting on Wood; framed 13 X 11 in.; unframed 10 X 8 in.
    - Wagon, 18; Tsegi
      Glass Etching; framed 12.5 X 14.5 in.; unframed 7.5 X 9.5 in.
    - San Jacinto Battlefield 490.01, 19; Holmes, Dwight C.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 14 X 12 in.; unframed 11.5 X 9.5 in.
    - Paisano Peak in Davis Mountains 404.01, 20; Brashear, Dorothy Lewallen
      Handbook of Texas Online. "Paisano Peak (Brewster County)." Accessed September 8, 2017.
      Painted on Canvas; framed 17 X 21 in.; unframed 11.5 X 15.5 in.
    - Building at Washington-on-the-Brazos Where Texas' Declaration of Independence was Signed on March 2, 1836, 21; Searcy, R.B.
      pencil on paper; framed 25.5 X 37.5 in.; unframed 24 X 36 in.
    - Collision at Crush Texas, 22; Abernathy, Robert R
      Colored Pencil Drawing; framed 49.5 X 98 in.; unframed 44 X 92 in.
    - Bluebonnets 302.1000, 23; Unknown, Artist
      Oil Painting; framed 10.5 X 14 in.; unframed 6.5 X 10 in.
    - "Tio Vive" Taos, 24; Mayslen, Barbara
      Black Print; framed 22 X 18 in.; unframed 14 X 12.5 in.
    - Texas Capital at Houston 414.01, circa 1935; Artist, Unknown
      Physical Description
      General condition: Good.
      Print; framed 9.84 X 10.63 in.
  - Donald Yena, 10
    - San José y San Miguel de Aguayo [Mission San José] 1971.06.02, 1; Yena, Donald M.
      Mission San José y San Miguel de Aguayo (San Antonio, Tex.); San Antonio (Tex.) -- History.; Spanish mission buildings -- Texas -- San Antonio.
      oil on canvas; framed 36 X 46 in.; unframed 22 X 32.25 in.
    - Nuestra Senora la Loreto [Presideo la Bahía] 1971.06.01, 2; Yena, Donald M.
      Goliad (Tex.) -- History.; Presidio La Bahía (Tex.) -- History.
    - San Francisco de la Espada [Mission Espada] 1971.06.05, 3; Yena, Donald M.
      Mission San Francisco de la Espada (San Antonio, Tex.); San Antonio (Tex.) -- History.; Spanish mission buildings -- Texas -- San Antonio.
      oil on canvas; framed 35.5 X 46.5 in.; unframed 21 X 32 in.
    - San Juan Capistrano [Mission San Juan] 1971.06.06, 4; Yena, Donald M.
      Mission San Juan Capistrano (San Antonio, Tex.); San Antonio (Tex.) -- History.; Spanish mission buildings -- Texas -- San Antonio.
      oil on canvas; framed 35.5 X 46.25 in.; unframed 21 X 32 in.
    - San Antonio de Valero [The Alamo], 5; Yena, Donald M.
      Alamo (San Antonio, Tex.) -- History.; Mission San Antonio de Valero -- History.; San Antonio (Tex.) -- History.; Spanish mission buildings -- Texas -- San Antonio.
    - Purisma Concepción de Acuna [Mission Concepción], 6; Yena, Donald M.
      Mission Concepción (San Antonio, Tex.); San Antonio (Tex.) -- History.; Spanish mission buildings -- Texas -- San Antonio.
  - Erwin M. Hearne, 11
    - The Arrest of George W. Slaughter 1137, 1; Hearne, Erwin M.
      George Webb Slaughter, Baptist preacher and rancher in Texas, is being arrested in this painting for attempting to hold a Protestant church service in Mexican Texas.
      Slaughter, George Webb, 1811-1894.
      oil on canvas; framed 35.75 X 29.25 in.; unframed 30.25 X 24 in.
    - The First Baptist Newspaper in Texas 1233, 2; Hearne, Erwin M.
      oil on canvas; framed 36 X 29.75 in.; unframed 29.5 X 23.5 in.
    - Confederate Troops on Baylor Campus at Independence 1232, 3; Hearne, Erwin M.
      During the American Civil War, 143 men from Baylor University entered the Confederate forces. During the war, Confederate forces were granted temporary use of university buildings. The President's house, built by Rufus C. Burleson, became military headquarters for the Confederate troops.
      Baylor University (Independence, Tex.) -- History.; Baylor University -- History, Military.; Texas -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
      oil on canvas; framed 37.5 X 31.75 in.; unframed 29.5 X 23.75 in.
    - Scene of Pioneers Crossing River on Raft 350.01, 4; Hearne, Erwin M.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 37.5 X 32 in.; unframed 30 X 23.5 in.
    - Signing of the Charter for Baylor University, Washington-on-the-Brazos, February 1, 1845 1488, 5; Hearne, Erwin M.
      This painting shows what the chartering of Baylor University might have looked like. Standing at the far end of the table is Judge R.E.B. Baylor, with James Huckins seated at his left, and William Tryon writing in the name Baylor University. Anson Jones, President of the Republic of Texas, in the foreground, with President of the Senate Kenneth Anderson and Speaker of the House John M. Lewis ready to affix their signatures to the official document.
      Baylor University (Independence, Tex.) -- History.; Baylor, R. E. B. (Robert Emmett Bledsoe), 1793-1873.; Historic buildings -- Texas-- Independence -- Pictorial works.; Huckins, James, 1807-1863.; Jones, Anson, 1798-1858.; Tryon, William Milton, 1809-1847.
      oil on canvas; framed 37.75 X 32 in.; unframed 29.5 X 23.5 in.
    - Baylor Presidents Brooks and Neff 1230, 6; Hearne, Erwin M.
      Dr. Samuel Palmer Brooks (right), President of Baylor University from 1902 to 1931, confers with Board President Pat M. Neff in "Prexy" Office shortly before President Brooks's composition of his immortal message to seniors and his eventual death. Neff gave the funeral eulogy for his former roommate and succeeded him as President of Baylor University.
      Brooks, Samuel Palmer, 1863-1931.; Neff, Pat Morris, 1871-1952.
      oil on canvas; framed 36 X 29.5 in.; unframed 29.5 X 23.25 in.
    - Baylor Opens Law School 1487, 7; Hearne, Erwin M.
      Baylor University opened law classes at Independence in 1858 when Judge R.E.B. Baylor and Judge Abner Smith Lipscomb volunteered to give law lectures. Benches from the Independence Baptist Church were used in the first classroom. Judge John Sayles and Judge Royal T. Wheeler later joined the staff.
      Baylor University (Independence, Tex.) -- History.; Baylor, R. E. B. (Robert Emmett Bledsoe), 1793-1873.; Historic buildings -- Texas-- Independence -- Pictorial works.; Independence (Tex.).
      oil on canvas; framed 29.5 X 36 in.; unframed 24 X 30.25 in.
    - First Campus of Baylor University 1231, 8; Hearne, Erwin M.
      Rufus C. Burleson, Baylor's president from 1851-1861, surveys the Independence campus, seeking God's guidance in serving students--those present and those to come.
      Baylor University (Independence, Tex.) -- History.; Burleson, Rufus Columbus, 1823-1901.; Historic buildings -- Texas-- Independence -- Pictorial works.; Independence (Tex.).
      oil on canvas; framed 32 X 37.5 in.; unframed 24.75 X 30.5 in.
    - The First Baptist Sunday School in Texas, 9; Hearne, Erwin M.
      Christian education -- Texas.
    - Mrs. J.M. Dawson and Women's Memorial Dormitory, 10; Hearne, Erwin M.
      Baylor University -- Buildings.
    - First Baptist Foreign Missionaries from Texas, the Bagbys, 11; Hearne, Erwin M.
      Bagby, Anne Ellen Luther, 1859-.; Bagby, William Buck, 1855-.
  - General, 12
    - Infare worn by Cora Wilson McLennan, Wife of first Sheriff of McLennan County 463.01, 1; Unknown, Artist
      Fabric; framed 25.5 X 21.5 in.; unframed 19 X 15 in.
    - Piece of Garrison Flag 347.01, 1861; 2; Herbst, Charles
      Piece of Flag; framed 13.5 X 8 in.; unframed 11.5 X 6.5 in.
    - Painting of a Clock at 6:58, 3; Unknown, Artist
    - Door & Steps, 4; Lake, Mary
      Painting on Paper; framed 21.5 X 25 in.; unframed 15.5 X 19 in.
  - Henry A. McArdle
    Test
    - Cora Lewis Bryan, 1889; McArdle, Henry Arthur
    - Ira Randolph Lewis, 1891; McArdle, Henry Arthur
    - Chauncey Berkeley Shepard, 1889; McArdle, Henry Arthur
    - Moses Austin Bryan, 1889; McArdle, Henry Arthur
    - Eliza Julia Hunt Lewis, 1889; McArdle, Henry Arthur
    - Mary Hester Andrews Shepard, circa 1839; 1; McArdle, Henry Arthur
  - John French, circa 1972
    - Jane Wilkinson Long, circa 1972; 1; French, John
      Frontier and pioneer life -- Texas.; Painting -- Texas.; Women -- Texas.
    - Mary Austin Holley, circa 1972; 2; French, John
      Authors -- Women -- Texas.; Painting -- Texas.; Women -- Texas.
    - Suzanna Dickinson, circa 1972; 3; French, John
      Alamo (San Antonio, Tex.) -- History.
    - Cynthia Ann Parker, circa 1972; 4; French, John
      Parker, Cynthia Ann, 1827?-1864.
      Frontier and pioneer life -- Texas.; Indian captivities -- Texas.; Painting -- Texas.; Women -- Texas.
    - Margaret Moffette Lea Houston, circa 1972; 5; French, John
    - Elisabet Ney, circa 1972; 6; French, John
      Ney, Elisabet, 1833-1907.
      Painting -- Texas.; Women -- Texas.
    - Mollie Bailey, circa 1972; 7; French, John
    - Miriam Amanda Ferguson, circa 1972; 8; French, John
      Texas -- Politics and government.
      Painting -- Texas.; Women -- Texas.; Women and Politics -- History.
- General Landscapes, 3
  - Landscape 1267, 1; Salings, Porfirio
    Oil on Canvas; framed 25 X 31.5 in.; unframed 17.5 X 23.5 in.
  - 1903, 2; Breustedt, Lillian
    Painting WaterColor?; framed 26 X 30 in.; unframed 17 X 21 in.
  - Riverscene, 3; Barnes, Elizabeth
    Painting; framed 29 X 43 in.; unframed 24 X 38 in.
  - Painting of Windmill (Dutch landscape) 418.01, 4; Unknown, Artist
    Painting on Wood; framed 33 X 19 in.; unframed 27.5 X 13.5 in.
  - Waterfall 302.1001, 5; Unknown, Artist
    Painting on Wood; framed 17.5 X 10.5 in.; unframed 14.5 X 7.5 in.
  - Scenery 369.01, 6; Graves, Bettie Williams
    Artist Bettie Williams Graves was daughter of Henry Lee Graves, first president of Baylor University.
    Oil on Canvas; framed 44 X 54.5 in.; unframed 37 X 48 in.
  - Scenery 2 368.01, 7; Graves, Bettie Williams
    Artist Bettie Williams Graves was daughter of Henry Lee Graves, first president of Baylor University. She completed the painting when she was fifteen years old.
    Oil On Canvas; framed 44.5 X 52.5 in.; unframed 37.5 X 46 in.
  - Tree, undated; 8